So there are other duties of directors under
CAMA 2020.
CAMA 2020 is the Communist and Allied Matters
Act.
These duties include that directors are reminded that
they are trustees of the company and as
such they should manage the property of the
company in its best interest.
They have the responsibility of ensuring the accuracy
of the financial statements and this duty cannot
be delegated.
So whilst the CFO has been appointed by
the board to oversee the integrity of the
financial statements, that responsibility remains with the board.
It cannot abdicate that responsibility.
Directors also have a responsibility to the environment
and I think this is more so now
that there's a lot of conversation around ESG
and matters relating to taking care of the
environment.
The board has a responsibility to measure and
monitor performance.
It has to measure its own performance.
Typically the board will set key performance indicators
against which its performance will be measured per
period.
It can set such performance indicators as oversights
of succession planning, oversights of KPIs for management,
oversights of so many things and then at
the end of the year it can measure
how well it has done.
But under this head the most critical responsibility
of the board is to measure the performance
of management and typically what the board does
or should do is to set key performance
indicators not just financial because a lot of
boards unfortunately end up setting only financial indicators.
Typically they set a budget and if the
budget is achieved it's heuristic to management.
However, an effective board should go beyond setting
financial indicators for management.
So things like staff attrition, stakeholder engagements, even
engagement with the board itself, leadership alignments, oversight
of strategy would go into the CEO's appraisal
and the CEO would also cascade this to
his own reports including the EEDs.
And beyond setting the KPIs the board also
has to put in place a process for
measuring, for appraising performance against the KPIs that
has been set.
The board also has a responsibility to define
a remuneration policy for itself, that is for
directors as well as for executive management.
And most of the time there's a portion
of executive management remuneration that is linked to
performance which is why setting KPIs and measuring
the KPIs is critical.
Further going into the duties and responsibilities is
one for ensuring that there's a risk management
framework in place.
The board has to define the risk appetite
and the risk capacity as well as the
risk limits of the organisation.
In this regard an enterprise risk management framework
is in place and that is monitored per
period.
Reports in this regard are expected to be
presented to the board at its quarterly meetings.
The board also has oversight of risk governance
with clear rules and responsibilities for the effective
discharge of responsibilities in this regard.